Today's דף daf is מ"ט. mem-tet. We're going to pick up from
the bottom of מ"ח עמוד ב mem-chet amud bet where it says
לימא
כתנאי leima katannai המלווה את חבירו hamalveh et chaveiro six seven lines
from the bottom with the asterisk. So let me just sort of
recap where we're up to. We just finished the whole major debate
of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish whether biblically
we know that as a practical matter משיכה meshicha is the active
קנין kinyan on מטלטלין metaltelin on chattel, but there's a debate what
the biblical issue is. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says that is the
biblical issue way it's defined. But רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says no,
no, no, biblically it goes by כסף kesef by money. The rabbis
instituted משיכה meshicha because they wanted the owner of the object to
have possession of the object in case anything went wrong with the
object, you know, you shouldn't have that responsibility or whatever, it shouldn't
be something that that I could lose my object because I haven't
taken possession of it yet and you weren't watching it well. So
the object is only transferred when it's taken possession of. So that's
why they overwrote the biblical institution of כסף. kesef. There's an interesting
debate what did we rule like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan or ריש
לקיש? Reish Lakish? It's not clear how we rule. Long תוספות Tosafot
discusses that. There's also a very interesting debate and this I don't
know if this was touched on but it certainly was a running
theme of the last few דפים dappim about how to conceptualize רבי
יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. When רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that the rabbis
came and instituted משיכה meshicha as opposed to the biblical כסף kesef
was he saying that the biblical כסף kesef does nothing and it
no longer is effective at all and the only thing that effects
the transfer is the משיכה meshicha or is he saying that the
biblical כסף kesef actually works but you have a right then to
choose to to reverse it and you have the ability to sort
of retract until the משיכה meshicha is done? But that still but
if you gave the money it works until until you've reversed it
it still works biblically. So we saw that possibility emerge from the
position in the משנה mishna I think it was רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon that says that only the person with the money can retract.
The person who has not yet taken the object, the purchaser who
has not yet taken the object, cannot retract. So that makes it
clear that the actual giving of the money makes the sale valid,
but there's a right to negate it and to retract it. And
according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that right is only on one
side. If we rule that both sides can
retract the question is left open. Is it a right to retract
or is it that the sale never was binding? And that also
plays out in terms of the whole issue of the מי שפרע
Mi Sheparah that the גמרא Gemara says that if one side retracts
they get a מי שפרע. Mi Sheparah. If you just promise to
go through with a sale and you say to do a sale
and you change your mind then that was the גמרא's Gemara's discussion
of whether דברים יש בהם משום מחוסרי אמנה devarim yesh bahem mishum
mechusrei amana whether your verbal agreement right I mean that's a question
in English secular law as well verbal contract whether your verbal agreement
is there any moral problem? There's certainly not a הלכתי halachic problem.
Is there even any moral problem about backing out? And the גמרא
Gemara maybe made distinctions like it's one thing to back out because
of changed circumstances, right? It's another thing to back out because you've
just changed your mind and especially if the other person is relying
on you. Okay so but even if you do back out of
those things in a way that's inappropriate שארית ישראל לא יעשו עולה
she-eiris Yisrael lo ya'asu avlah right the Jewish people should not do
any perversion, nevertheless but you don't get a מי שפרע. Mi Sheparah.
The מי שפרע Mi Sheparah that curse or that promise that God
will pay you back is only if you've paid money and then
back out or one side backs out after money has paid. So
why is that? Is it the paying of money makes it more
like you've concretized your commitment and people are more relying on you
and therefore it's like worse morally to back out? Or a different
way to look at it, a legal different way to look at
it is when you pay the money actually the sale is binding
biblically speaking according to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. And when you back
out you've actually reversed a sale that was binding. So it's not
like it was never binding, it was binding, you just had the
right to reverse it. So that is a very important conceptual question
according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan when we say דאורייתא d'raita the
money does it is it that the rabbis completely erased that or
is it that no, that still works but you can just override?
And you're still getting a מי שפרע Mi Sheparah for that? Well
you get a מי שפרע Mi Sheparah once money changed hands. No,
you don't get the מי שפרע Mi Sheparah if money didn't change
hands. Yeah, you get the money back but you reversed a deal.
Okay, so that is the question or that's the very critical question
within רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Now I should say רש"י Rashi even
says a possible נפקא מינה nafka mina would be let's say I
go ahead and I give Michael money and I don't do משיכה
meshicha for Michael I don't know apple or something and then I
don't take the apple but I go to this woman who I've
who I who I want to marry and I say הרי את
מקודשת לי harey at mekudeshet li with this apple and she picks
it up like I never pick it up. Okay
anyway and I never pick it up. So I've never done a
קנין kinyan on it but I did pay money for it. Is
she married? And רש"י Rashi basically says that according to one way
of understanding רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan she is still married as long
as we haven't reversed it then that קנין kinyan of giving the
money is binding. So that's a very, very important point. So that's
a very, very important למעשה l'maaseh type of halachic question of how
to conceptualize the giving of the money according to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan. Now that translates into the discussion that the גמרא Gemara just
had that we're going to now continue with, which is the discussion
about whether when you give a partial payment, is it קונה כנגד
כולו koneh k'neged kulo or קונה כנגדו? koneh k'negdo? Now that could
be the simple case is a case of קרקע karka which is
קונה koneh with כסף. kesef. So if I go ahead and I
buy something for a million dollars, a thousand acres, and I
give let's say half of it, a five hundred thousand, but let's
say I give a thousand, let's say I give a hundred dollars.
Now do I purchase the entire land or only a hundred dollars
worth of it? And there the גמרא Gemara says that by קרקע
karka it seems that you purchase all of it. Okay. Since קרקע
karka fundamentally works by כסף, kesef, then we basically look at it
as though I now owe you the rest. It's a mortgage essentially.
I've given you this as the initial act of payment, and it's
as if I've given you all the rest of the money and
borrowed it back and have it as a loan, but it's as
if I've already paid you for the whole thing. That's actually what
you do with a mortgage. The bank pays the person and you
owe the bank. So here it's as if I paid you and
now I owe you the rest of the money, but it's like
I've paid in full. So that's basically what we say by קרקע.
karka. The question becomes what do we say by מטלטלין? metaltelin? And
now the only relevance for this question by מטלטלין metaltelin is do
I get a מי שפרע? mi she-para? Okay. I agree to sell
you a hundred bushels of apples for a dollar a bushel. You
give me five dollars. And now you want to back out. So
if you back out and not take any bushels and get your
five dollars back, then you get a מי שפרע mi she-para because
at least five dollars worth of apples you bought. But let's say
you say, you know what? Fine. I'll take the first five bushels,
but I don't want to do the other ninety-five. Do you get
a מי שפרע? mi she-para? Is it like you've paid money on
the rest and now by backing out you're going to get a
מי שפרע mi she-para on the rest? So that's the question of
כנגדו k'negdo or כנגד כולו. k'neged kulo. And here again the language
of the גמרא Gemara is very indicative because the language of the
גמרא Gemara is כנגדו הוא קונה k'negdo hu koneh or כנגד כולו
הוא קונה. k'neged kulo hu koneh. Right? So it sounds like even
when you're dealing with מטלטלין metaltelin and we're dealing with money, that
the money actually effects the קנין, kinyan, that either... and this would
work very beautifully according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, that biblically the
money is what does it, so you've actually purchased the object, but
you have a right to retract, and therefore we want to know
when you pay part of it, have you purchased just that part
or have you purchased the whole thing? Okay, but that is the
question that we ask by מטלטלין metaltelin when you're doing a partial
payment and you want to have... is there going to be a
מי שפרע mi she-para if you retract not from the amount you
paid for but from the remainder of the amount? And that's the
debate: רב Rav and רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. רב Rav says that
it's כנגדו k'negdo and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that it's כנגד
כולו. k'neged kulo. Some questions. Yes, Michael. So I understand it's easier
in the case of bushels of apples, you know, I'll give you
five bushels. What if you're buying a cow? Yeah, yeah, so that's
a very good question. Yeah, so it's a good question. I don't
know, you're right, and maybe there we would say it clearly is
כנגד כולו. k'neged kulo. That's certainly more reason to say if it's
an indivisible unit it's כנגד כולו. k'neged kulo. But yes, that's the
right question to ask. Yes. The מי שפרע mi she-para is because
you went back on your word, right? Or because you retracted a
binding sale. Right, so depending on how you conceptualize.
So that's what we said... that's what I said before, I don't
know, maybe I was saying it too fast, but that if you
did not actually pay the money, you just verbally committed to do
it and you back out, you do not get a מי שפרע.
mi she-para. You know, you're told that that's not the right thing
to do, okay, and depending on... that's a question of דברים שיש
בהם משום מחוסרי אמנה. devarim she-yesh bahem mishum mechusrei amana. How bad
was it to do is a function about whether the circumstances changed
or did you just arbitrarily change your mind? How much did the
other side rely on your commitment to do it? Okay, but either
way you don't get a מי שפרע. mi she-para. Okay, it's not
right to do that under certain circumstances but you don't get a
מי שפרע. mi she-para. Charlie, yes. This seems to have some implications
for how we do the מכירת חמץ? mechirat chametz? I'm not gonna...
I can't process that right now. Yes, sorry. Really simple question.
Would you say that at the underlying this entire סוגיא sugya in
a way is what do we mean conceptually by to give something
to somebody? Right, משיכה meshichah is like it requires a concrete actual
experience with the item itself. How far can you abstract the concept
conceptually what it means that I've given you something when you haven't
really actually held onto it yet?
I give you the money, so I've given it to you.
That's really interesting. Okay, I'm not sure I would... I hear what
you're saying. I mean to me it's like it's one side of
giving as opposed to the other side. We're not giving both directions,
so it's a question of which side is the one that effects
the sale. Yeah. Another question about this. The מי שפרע, mi she-para,
we didn't fully talk about this. Is it actually בית דין? Beis
Din? Let's say you know... Yeah, so that's also not clear. You
know, the גמרא... Gemara... right, I mean the גמרא Gemara basically... it
doesn't sound like anybody actually does the curse, but you know, it
is interesting that the גמרא Gemara has a question: is it just
we inform... person you should know God is going to pay you
back or is it actually the גמרא Gemara says like we curse
the person? And then who's the we? Are we actually doing a
curse or are we basically saying like, you know, you will be
cursed, you know, that curse exists, we the rabbis when we instituted
this idea of מי שפרע, Mi She-parah, you should know means we're
cursing anybody in the future who does this thing. It's also an
interesting question which is not fully clear that the גמרא Gemara sometimes
sort of speaks about have I agreed to accept the מי שפרע?
Mi She-parah? You know the question is like if I'm saying that
I'm basically going to like reverse it or not maybe it hasn't,
you know the גמרא Gemara came up before in the גמרא, Gemara,
you know maybe it's not actually reversed until I agree to accept
the מי שפרע Mi She-parah if I don't agree then I haven't
then my reversing is not binding it, you know, even if I
say I'm backing down whatever anyway. Alright let's move on. So now
the גמרא Gemara says the following on the bottom of מ"ח עמוד
ב'. Mem Ches Amud Beis. Okay לימא כתנאי, Leima Kesannai, let's say
this is a debate of Rav and Rabbi Yochanan כנגדו Kenegdo or
כנגד כולו Keneged Kullo is a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. המלווה את
חברו על המשכון, Hamalveh Es Chaveiro Al Hamashkon, you lend money to
your friend and you get a collateral ונכנסה השמיטה Venichnesah Hashmitah and
then it became the שמיטה Shmitah year אף על פי שאינו שווה
אלא פלג Af Al Pi She-eino Shaveh Ela Palg even though the
משכון Mashkon is only worth half of the loan אינו משמט, Eino
Meshamet, שמיטה Shmitah does not annul the loan דברי רבי שמעון בן
גמליאל, Divrei Rabbi Shimon Ben Gamliel, that's what Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel
says. רבי יהודה הנשיא אומר, Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi Omer, Rabbi says, Rabbi
Yehuda HaNasi says אם היה משכון כנגד הלוואתו אינו משמט, Im Hayah
Mashkon Keneged Halvahso Eino Meshamet, sure if the collateral was equivalent to
the loan then it does not annul because the reason שמיטה Shmitah
annuls it says לא יגוש את רעהו ואת אחיו, Lo Yigos Es
Re'eihu Ve'es Achiv, you should not somehow like extract it from your
friend like oppress even your friend. So therefore if you actually have
the money by you, if you have the collateral by you you
don't have to extract it then it is not relevant to the
laws of שמיטה, Shmitah, so שמיטה Shmitah is only that act of
of exertion of a you know exercising of power and extracting and
therefore if it's already in your possession it's not that act and
therefore שמיטה Shmitah does not annul the loan. So Rabbi says that's
only true if the משכון Mashkon is equivalent to the entire loan
אם היה משכון כנגד הלוואתו אינו משמט Im Hayah Mashkon Keneged Halvahso
Eino Meshamet ואם לאו Ve'im Lav and if not משמט Meshamet it
does. Now which part of the loan are they debating? The part
right when it's only half the loan you know if are they
debating so that's the גמרא's Gemara going to say מאי אינו משמט
דקאמר רבי שמעון בן גמליאל Mai Eino Meshamet De-kamar Rabbi Shimon Ben
Gamliel and Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel says that שמיטה Shmitah does not
annul it, which part of the loan is he referring to? אילימא
כנגדו Ileima Kenegdo if he means that it is not does not
annul the part that the value of the משכון Mashkon itself let's
make it easy let's not make it fifty-fifty the loan was worth
a thousand dollars and the משכון Mashkon was worth two hundred okay
so which part of the loan is so so what are they
debating the two hundred or the eight hundred? Okay so אילימא כנגדו
Ileima Kenegdo Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel is saying oh at least for
the two hundred dollars of the משכון Mashkon you possess that that
שמיטה Shmitah does not annul מכלל דרבי יהודה הנשיא סבר להאי פלגא
נמי משמט, Mikhral De-Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi Savar Le-hai Palga Nami Meshamet, would
that mean to imply that according to Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi it would
annul even the two hundred dollars of the loan? How could it
annul the two hundred dollars of it? Two hundred dollars you're fully
in possession of everybody should agree it can't annul that. אלא Ela
it seems top of מ"ט עמוד א' Mem Tes Amud Aleph אלא
משכון דנקיט למה לי Ela Mashkon Denakit Lamei Leh why are you
holding onto the משכון? Mashkon? Clearly the two hundred the value of
it is at least that you can collect two hundred dollars worth
of the loan so at least two hundred dollars of the loan
is in your possession so שמיטה Shmitah should be more than the
two hundred well but no no but everybody should agree the שמיטה
Shmitah should not be משמט Meshamet the two hundred dollars because that's
already in your possession. אלא לאו Ela Lav so if they're debating
what it's משמט Meshamet שמע מינה מאי אינו משמט דקאמר רבי שמעון
בן גמליאל Shema Mina Mai Eino Meshamet De-kamar Rabbi Shimon Ben Gamliel
what does it mean it's not משמט? Meshamet? אינו משמט בכולו Eino
Meshamet Bekullo it means that he's saying that as long as you
have a partial possession of the loan it is it's like you're
possessing all of it and none of the loan is annulled ומאי
משמט דקאמר רבי יהודה הנשיא U-mai Meshamet De-kamar Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi and
when Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi says it it is annulled להאי פלגא Le-hai
Palga it means that the part that you're not possessing the eight
hundred that it's annulling דלא נקיט עליה משכון Delo Nakit Alei Mashkon
that you're not holding a משכון Mashkon wait a minute ובהא קמיפלגי
U-vaha Kamiflegi and this is the debate we're on מ"ט עמוד א'
Mem Tes Amud Aleph רבי שמעון בן גמליאל סבר כנגד כולו הוא
קונה Rabbi Shimon Ben Gamliel Savar Keneged Kullo Hu Koneh Rabbi Shimon
ben Gamliel says that you are purchasing opposite all of it now
of course this is an analogy because this is not the same
as when I give money in an exchange but my holding of
the משכון Mashkon somehow represents a holding of the whole loan and
since I'm holding the entire
loan therefore שמיטה's Shmitah not משמט Meshamet anything because I'm holding the
entire
loan ורבי יהודה הנשיא סבר כנגדו הוא קונה Ve-Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi Savar
Kenegdo Hu Koneh and Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi says no you're only holding
the amount of the loan that you're holding you're holding two hundred
dollars so it's not משמט Meshamet the two hundred dollars but the
rest it is משמט. Meshamet. Now that's a very nice explanation of
Rabbi and Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel when you're holding a משכון Mashkon
is it representative of holding the whole loan? The only thing is
that I don't exactly understand how it's the same question of when
I pay you money is it like I've paid you for everything
and I owe you the rest or is it like I've just
paid you for that portion? Right? I mean like in you can
sort of argue different things in different cases like the משכון Mashkon
could represent the whole loan but when I'm paying you for something
I've only bought the amount that I've bought you know? Here there's
already money I've lent you and you're giving me something and what
is that thing supposed to represent? It's a different type of a
question but it's analogous, okay? I mean the ראשונים, rishonim, I haven't
seen the ראשונים rishonim really try to connect the dots, right? But
you understand that it's not the same, one is a question about
what I pay you partially, right? Do I, have I already bought
the whole thing? And the other is a question when I've loaned
you money and you give me a משכון. mashkon. I mean clearly
I don't physically have possession of the entire loan, I only have
possession of $200. It's more a question of does it represent the
entire loan, you know? Anyway, but it's somewhat analogous, okay? So the
גמרא Gemara says let's say that's our debate. So שמיטה shemittah will
not be משמט meshamet any loan if the borrower is holding a
משכון mashkon according to that? Yes, correct. And then what is the
problem of פרוזבול, pruzbul, right? All I have to do is make
certain that the borrower has a משכון. mashkon. Right, so that's a
good point. I mean you could ask why הלל Hillel had to
do it. But not everybody, you know, gives collateral. Somebody who's really
poor and has nothing or whatever and that's primarily the people that
this was meant to help, you know? They would not have a
משכון mashkon to give. Right, but you raise a good point. According
to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, you know, you
give a $1 משכון, mashkon, everybody just gives a $1 משכון mashkon
and it solves the problem. That is true. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay. ורמינהו ונוקמינהו בתרי תנאי.
U-re-mi-hu u-nok-mi-ne-hu b'trei tannai. לא, lo, לא, lo, it's not necessarily the
debate. מאי אינו משמט דקתני רבן שמעון בן גמליאל? Mai eino meshamet
d'katanei Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel? להאי פלגא דנקיט עליה משכון? L'hai palga
d'nakit alei mashkon? No, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
maybe just means that for that $200, it's not משמט meshamet because
that you are totally in possession of. מכלל דרבי יהודה הנשיא סבר
להאי פלגא דנקיט עליה משכון נמי משמט? Miklal d'Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi savar
l'hai palga d'nakit alei mashkon nami meshamet?
You mean to say that that's true, they're debating about whether the
$200 is annulled? That רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say even the
$200 משכון mashkon you're holding, even $200 of the loan is annulled?
אלא משכון דנקיט למה לי? Ela mashkon d'nakit lamah li? Why are
you holding the משכון? mashkon? Clearly the holding of the משכון mashkon
is to be in possession of at least part of the loan.
So if you're in possession of it, how could שמיטה shemittah be
משמט meshamet that $200? So the גמרא Gemara says: לזכרון דברים בעלמא.
L'zikron devarim be'alma. No, the משכון, mashkon, especially you could say this
is true if the משכון mashkon is less than the full value
of the loan, right? As the גמרא Gemara said before, normally you
have your collateral on something worth more than the loan. You want
to make sure you're getting your money back. So if the משכון
mashkon is worth less than the loan, it says it's really just
there as to remember. The fact that I'm holding onto your object
means that I am constantly being reminded of the fact I am
not going to forget you owe me the money, maybe I'm going
to nudge you more for the money, maybe I'll use it as
a little bit of leverage to get you to give me the
money, but it is not yet a possession of payment for the
loan. Certainly if it is less than the value of the loan,
then it really more is just purely symbolic and it does not
really sense a possessing the loan in any way. So according to
this debate, they're debating what it means to hold onto a משכון
mashkon less than the value, are you in possession of the value
of the משכון? mashkon? So there's an answer to your Rabbi Dov,
according to that read, you have not solved the פרוזבול pruzbul problem,
because it only prevents שמיטה shemittah even according to רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel only prevents שמיטה shemittah from operating on
the amount you're in possession of. So according to that, according to
that interpretation, this משכון mashkon in a way becomes a פיקדון, pikadon,
like I'm a שומר? shomer? Yeah, well that's an interesting question in
general about משכון, mashkon, what your level of liability is to it,
but yes. Okay, and according to the first way, you can't say
that. מהו יכלי למימר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל סבר דאינו משמט Mahu
yachli le-meimar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel savar d'eino meshamet still not משמט
meshamet the whole at all, any part of the loan, even though
it's not worth... Yeah, but we don't want to say that because
we want to move it out of the debate of כנגדו k'negdo
or כנגד כולו. k'neged kulo. I mean it's true, you could have
them go to opposite extremes, that's true, but then to some degree
at least רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel would still
be saying כנגד כולו k'neged kulo and we want to move it
out of that discussion. Okay, but that's a valid way of explaining.
Yeah, yeah, correct. Okay, now, now we're going to talk about, so
we still don't know, it's a debate now of רבא Rava and
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, is it כנגדו k'negdo or כנגד כולו? k'neged
kulo? Let's take a look. רב כהנא יהבו ליה זוזי אכיתנא. Rav
Kahana yahavu lei zuzei a-kitna. Rav Kahana, they gave him money for
flax, okay? He was a flax seller. What I love about these
stories is you get to see how many professions the rabbis were
involved in. Flax! No, come on! We have all these good stories.
Anyway, fine. Rav Kahana, maybe it was a... maybe it was a...
anyway. Rav Kahana, they gave him money for flax. לסוף אייקר כיתנא.
Le-sof aykar kitna. Then the price of flax went up. So he
wanted to back out, okay? He's always giving me flax...
he wanted to back out. אתא לקמיה דרב. Ata l'kamei d'Rav. Now,
he knew who to ask the שאלה she'eilah for because רב, Rav,
remember, says כנגדו. k'negdo. So they didn't give him the full value.
If they gave him the full value and he would have backed
out he would have gotten a מי שפרע. mi she-para. They only
paid him a down payment. So he was not going to back
out on the amount they paid him for, they did not... he
did not want a מי שפרע. mi she-para. But he wanted to
back out on the remainder of it, okay? So he asked רב.
Rav. רב Rav is the one who says כנגדו, k'negdo, not כנגד
כולו. k'neged kulo. Where did the משכון mashkon go? You don't... it's
not a משכון. mashkon. We're out of משכון. mashkon. They paid him
partially for the flax, okay? אתא לקמיה דרב. Ata l'kamei d'Rav. אמר
ליה: Amar lei: במאי דנקיטת זוזי, b'mai d'nakitat zuzei, the amount that
you have money that you've taken, הב להו, hav le-hu, corresponding to
that amount give them the flax, ואידך, ve-idach, the remainder of it,
דברים נינהו, devarim ninhu, it's only a verbal commitment. The money was
not yet considered paid... it wasn't considered yet paid for for the
remainder. The remainder's a verbal commitment. ודברים אין בהם משום מחוסרי אמנה.
u-devarim ein ba-hem mishum mechusrei amanah. And דברים devarim is not a
concern of backing up... of like of violating trust, a violation of
trust. Trust. And therefore, if it's not—oh, I'm sorry. When I was
giving my overview, I anticipated this, but I got lost what we
had covered and what we hadn't covered. Okay, so anyway, so now
you'll see it in retrospect, it'll all make sense. But anyway, I
gave you a preview of what we're about to see. So here
is the debate about whether when it is not money paid, right,
money paid you get the מי שפרע Mi shepara, *Mi Sheparah*, either
because it's just a serious commitment that you're retracting, or because as
we said before, because of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. *Rabbi Yochanan*, maybe
even it was a binding agreement, maybe it even was a binding
sale that you're now reversing. So you get a מי שפרע mi
she-para, *Mi Sheparah* with money. But if we—but the—but if there's a
verbal commitment without money and you back out, how bad is it?
How much is it considered like I broke a verbal—I mean, legally
I'm allowed to, but is it ethically bad? I mean, in normal
secular law, I think sometimes you can actually be sued for violation
of a verbal contract. But here you—it—you cannot be sued, there's no
legal consequence, but is it ethically wrong to break a verbal commitment
and a verbal trust? And partly it might have to do with
well, what's your motivation? Like if it's part of business, you know,
the price went up or whatever, and it's more understandable, but if
I just arbitrarily changed my mind, maybe not. We'll see about this.
So רב Rav *Rav* says right, okay. So רב Rav *Rav* says,
so רב Rav *Rav* says, right, okay, fine. So רב Rav? *Rav*
says, so רב Rav, *Rav* is saying that two points. Number one
is that the money only works opposite the amount that, you know,
the amount that was that was your—commitment, that it's like it was
paid for, was only opposite the amount of money received. It's כנגדו
*kenegdo*, it's not כנגד כולו *keneged kulo*. So therefore, there's no מי
שפרע mi she-para. *Mi Sheparah* on the rest. And not only is
there no מי שפרע mi she-para. *Mi Sheparah* on the rest, it's
not even morally wrong to back out on the rest. It's only
a verbal commitment that's part of business. The price has changed, prices
change, you can back out, that's understood that that's part of doing
business. Okay, let's take a look. Okay. So, if you want to
be—if you want to have possession of it all, pay for it
all. What? One person's doing business also at the same time. And
everybody understands. So the point is once—he's going to have the bottom
taken out, is that right? Once everybody understands the rules, then it's
just knowing how to play by the rules, right? So if you
understand that if you haven't paid for it yet, I can back
out for the part not paid for, then you have to—then you
have to anticipate that and you have to make prop—take—do proper things,
right? You have to borrow the money and pay me for it
if you don't want me to back out, right? So as long
as everybody knows the rules, I do not see a problem here,
okay. And what about a down payment? What? What about a down
payment? Well, that's a good point. So then a down payment according
to that would only have maybe some type of like, you know,
like making feel to do the right thing. But here according to
רב Rav *Rav*, it wasn't even a sense of doing the right
thing, you're right. So a down payment actually, if you say כנגדו
*kenegdo* and you say דברים devarim, אין בהם משום מחוסרי אמנה mechusrei
amana *devarim ein bahem mishum mechussrei amana*, it basically means down payment
is nothing. Down payment is just partial payment for that part, you're
right. Okay, so let's take a look, okay. So that was רב
*Rav*'s position. Okay, רב *Rav* said A, it only is opposite the
amount you did, and the rest is a purely verbal commitment, and
I didn't hear what it was. I'll say—I'll repeat it. And a
pure—and a pure and a purely verbal commitment, a purely verbal commitment,
not only are you not legally bound, and not only is there
no מי שפרע mi she-para. *Mi Sheparah*, there's no—nothing morally incorrect in
backing out. Okay, we're going to see where the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
goes, okay. I see that everybody is very exercised about this. We'll
see where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* goes with this. The דברים devarim
אין בהם משום מחוסרי אמנה mechusrei amana. *devarim ein bahem mishum mechussrei
amana*, it's not a violation of trust. איתמר *itmar*, it was discussed,
דברים *devarim*, what if it's just a verbal commitment? רב אמר אין
בהם משום מחוסרי אמנה mechusrei amana *Rav amar ein bahem mishum mechussrei
amana*. So it's very interesting the parallel of רב *Rav* and רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, *Rabbi Yochanan*. רב *Rav* wants to give the buyer
as much latitude as possible, right? So he says, you know, or
the per—so he says, you know, A, it's only כנגדו *kenegdo*, not
כנגד כולו *keneged kulo*, or the seller I guess has much latitude.
Yeah, the seller's much latitude. It's only כנגדו *kenegdo*, not כנגד כולו
*keneged kulo*. And B, there's no—by going back on a verbal commitment,
it's not a violation of trust. רבי יוחנן אמר יש בהם משום
מחוסרי אמנה *Rabbi Yochanan amar yesh bahem mishum mechussrei amana*. No, if
you say you're going to do something and you back out, it
is a violation of trust and it is morally wrong. And—meaning if
I—as a seller or buyer? I can back out as a buyer
too. Yeah, yeah, it could be both ways. It could be both
ways. מתיבי *meitivi*. רבי יוסי בר יהודה אומר *Rabbi Yose bar Yehuda
omer*. רבי יוסי בר יהודה *Rabbi Yose bar Yehuda* says, מה תלמוד
לומר *mah talmud lomar*, what is meant by the verse הין צדק
Hin Tzedek. יהיה לך *hin tzedek yihiyeh lach*, you should have a—a
just measure, right? In terms of the, you know, your weights and
measures should be just. So והלא הין בכלל איפה היא *v'halo hin
bichlal eifah hi*. It says איפה צדק הין צדק Hin Tzedek יהיה
לך *eifah tzedek hin tzedek yihiyeh lach*. So איפה *eifah* is a
bigger measure than a הין *hin*. So, you know, if it says
your איפה *eifah* should be just, certainly your הין *hin* should be
just. I guess it's a קל וחומר *kal v'chomer*, right? If you
can't be a little off on your large measure, certainly you shouldn't
be a little off on your small measures, okay, cause obviously it's
a exponential. אלא לומר לך *ela lomar lach*, so why does it
have to say that your הין *hin* should be just? To tell
you לומר לך שהן שלך צדק ולאו שלך צדק *lomar lach she'hen
shelcha tzedek v'lav shelcha tzedek*. Your yes should be a yes and
your no should be a no. When you say yes, you're supp—that's
a great line. Yeah, when you say—and you say yes, then you—then
you have to live up to that commitment. And if you say
no, you have to stand by that. Like you know by parenting.
You say if you do that again you're going to—you're, you know,
you're not going to go out, you know, for to to be
with your friends. Oh alright, fine, go be with your friends or
whatever then you completely undermine your authority if you don't, you know,
if you don't keep by what you say you're going to do.
Okay. So anyway. Alright. So. Okay so therefore he says that you
have an obligation, some ראשונים Rishonim even articulate this as they believe
that he's saying it's דאורייתא de'oraita and not אסמכתא. asmakhta. You have
an obligation to keep by your commitments. By the way, that is
different than the question about like white lies, you know, as opposed
to deceptive lies. We saw in an earlier גמרא, Gemara you might
remember, about things that you're allowed to, right, remember in בבא מציעא,
Bava Metzia, תלמיד חכם talmid chacham only sort of fudges the truth
in three areas? Okay, you know, so that's not the same as
הין צדק. הין צדק is not saying like, oh, you're not allowed,
everything that comes out of your mouth has to be a hundred
percent true, you're not allowed to sometimes sort of make white lies
for the greater good. This is sort of saying that if you
promise to do something or say you're not going to do something,
you know, your promise, your commitment, you know, has to, you have
to stand behind that. Okay, שיהא הין שלך צדק ולאו שלך צדק.
Sheyehei hencha tzedek velavcha tzedek. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, ההוא, no, no,
no. So doesn't that prove against רב that you can't back out
of a verbal commitment? So אביי Abaye says, no. ההוא שלא ידבר
אחד בפה ואחד בלב. Hahu shelo yedaber echad bapeh ve'echad balev. That
means you should not be duplicitous. That means that you should not
say one thing and not, you know, and not be sincere about
it when you're saying it, to say you're going to do it
and not plan to do it. Okay, but if you're sincere when
you say it, but you change your mind later, well people change
their mind. Okay, and, you know, and therefore you are not, there's
not a problem if you change your mind to go back on
what you said you were going to do, which is, it's troubling,
right, that you don't even have some sense here of some like
moral, you know, responsibility to do it. Okay, let's keep on going,
see where the גמרא Gemara goes with this.
מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask on this. רבי שמעון אומר אף על פי
שאמרו טלית קונה דינר זהב ואין דינר זהב קונה טלית, Rabbi Shimon
omer af al pi she'amru tallis koneh dinar zahav ve'ein dinar zahav
koneh tallis, even though they said when you take possession of the
טלית tallis you owe the gold
דינר, dinar, but if you take the דינר dinar you don't owe,
the other side doesn't own the טלית tallis yet. מכל מקום כך
הלכה. Mikol makom kach halakha. It's true that that is the הלכה
halakha as a legal point. אבל אמרו, Aval amru, but they said,
מי שפרע מאנשי דור המבול ומאנשי דור הפלגה הוא עתיד ליפרע ממי
שאינו עומד בדיבורו. Mi shepara me'anshei dor hamabul umianshei dor haflaga hu
asid lipara miman she'eino omed bediburo. Okay, the one who pays back
whatever, he in the end will, you know, punish the one who
does not stand behind his word. Now why is that a question?
Because that is, that's with paying money. So that doesn't prove דברים,
that's דברים with money. So רש"י Rashi says the proof is from
the end of the ברייתא. braita. You remember the end of the
ברייתא braita said that but when, and when no money changes hands,
you don't get a מי שפרע, mi she-para, but the phrase was,
what was the phrase before? It said when no money changes hands,
it said, הנושא ונותן בדברים לא קנה והחוזר בו אין רוח חכמים
נוחה הימנו. Hanosei venosein bidevarim lo kanah vehachozer bo ein ruach chachamim
nucha hemenu.
If it's a verbal commitment, there's no sense that the transaction is
binding, but if you retract it, the sages are disapproving of you.
Remember that from yesterday? Okay, that was the end of the ברייתא,
braita, that's the part we should be quoting here. So look, that
ברייתא braita says that if you retract a verbal commitment, the sages
are disapproving, so clearly there was something wrong with retracting a verbal
commitment, that backs רבי יוחנן. דברים יש בהם משום דמחוסרי אמנה. Devarim
yesh bahem mishum d'mechusrei amana.
So how do, what would רב say about this? So the גמרא
Gemara says, תנאי
היא. Tannai hi. Fine, it's a debate of
תנאים. Tannaim. דתנן, Detnan, מעשה ברבי יוחנן בן מתיא, Maaseh b'Rabbi Yochanan
ben Matsya, this is not רבי יוחנן, this was a תנא. Tanna.
שאמר לבנו, She'amar livno, and this is a משנה Mishnah coming up
later on, he said to his son, צא ושכור לנו פועלים, Tzei
us'chor lanu poalim, go hire for us some workers today. הלך ופסק
להם מזונות, Halach upasak lahem mezonot, he said fine, I'll pay you,
you know, a hundred dollars for the day plus lunch. Okay. וכשבא
אצל אביו, Ukesheba eitzel aviv,
when he came to the father, אמר לו, Amar lo, his father
said, בני אפילו אתה עושה להם כסעודת שלמה בשעתו לא יצאת ידי
חובתך עמהם שהן בני אברהם יצחק ויעקב. Bni afilu ata oseh lahem
kisedus Shlomo besha'ato lo yatzata yedei chovatcha imahem shehein bnei Avraham Yitzchak
v'Yaakov. When you promised them a meal, oh my god, you know,
it's always the, you know, what does it, the, the salary and
the benefits, the benefits are going to break the bank. Okay, it's
not just the salary. When you promised them, you know, you promised
them a meal, even were you to make to them like the
feast of שלמה המלך Shlomo Hamelech when he was at his greatest
height, לא יצאת ידי חובתך, lo yatzata yedei chovatcha, you would not
have satisfactorily fulfilled your obligation to feed them. עמהם שהן בני אברהם
יצחק ויעקב. Imahem shehein bnei Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov. They are descendants of
אברהם יצחק ויעקב. Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov. I don't know how that means
that they're supposed to get huge feasts but anyway, okay, they're sons
of kings. So anyway, so therefore you cannot promise them a meal
because we will not satisfy our obligation to them if you just
do it generically. אלא עד שלא יתחילו במלאכה צא ואמור להם על
מנת שאין לכם עלי אלא פת וקטנית בלבד. Ela ad shelo yatchilu
bamalacha tzei ve'emor lahem al menat she'ein lachem alai ela pas kikitnit
bilvad. Before they begin the work,
go say to them, when I said a meal, I want to
be clear, before you start work, all I'm obligated to do is
feed you like, you know, bread and some like porridge or whatever.
Okay, so anyway, what's relevant for us is that he was able
to change the terms of the deal before they began, before it
became binding. So you see that was not a problem of changing
the terms of the agreement. דברים יש בהם משום דמחוסרי אמנה. Devarim
yesh bahem mishum d'mechusrei amana. Right, obviously it's a little bit different.
ואי סלקא דעתך דברים יש בהם משום דמחוסרי אמנה היכי אמר ליה
אזיל הדר בך? Ve'ei salka deitach devarim yesh bahem mishum d'mechusrei amana
hechi amar lei azil hadar becha? If you say that there's a
problem of backing out of a verbal commitment, so how did he
say go change the agreement? So the גמרא Gemara. says, no. שאני
התם דפועלים גופייהו לא סמכא דעתייהו. Shani hatam depoalim gufaihu lo samcha
daataihu. No,
there anyway the workers had not totally, you know, relied upon that
commitment.
מאי טעמא מדידי. Mai tama mididi.
they know that the son is just relying on the father he's
just doing the father's bidding you know it's really the father who's
contracting with them so they understood they understood that you know that
it was not that it was somewhat pending the father's agreement. אי
הכי ee hachi says the Gemara אפילו התחילו במלאכה נמי afilu hitchilu
b'melacha nami even if they began the מלאכה melacha it's still pending
the father's agreement so it would not have been binding. So the
Gemara says no התחילו במלאכה ודאי סמכא דעתייהו hitchilu b'melacha vadai samcha
da'atayu if they're starting the work then it means that they're at
the assumption that it's now binding that the father is behind it.
אמרו amru they said מימר אמר קמיה דאבוה וניחא ליה meimar amar
kamei d'avua v'nicha lei at this stage he must have told the
father and since we didn't hear any revision it must be the
father's okay. Okay now the important principle for us though is that
even according to Rabbi Yochanan and this is going to come up
that דברים יש בהם משום מחוסרי אמנה devarim yesh bahem mishum mechusrei
amana that's only if the other side to some degree relies on
it. Now what does it mean relies on it? Does it mean
they forgo other opportunities? Does it just mean they're really hoping for
it? You know so what's the measure of reliance? But certainly if
I'm a guy that everybody knows I just say I make promises
that I don't keep it's like somewhat ironic you know but if
everybody knows I just talk a lot and never do it then
that's not מחוסרי אמנה because nobody ever trusts me to begin with
and relies upon it to agree with. Or if there's somehow an
assumption an understanding that you know that things might change and I
might not be able to go through with you know so it
limits Rabbi Yochanan. But that makes Rav's position even more radical that
Rav is then saying that even when the other side is relying
on it it's not a problem there's no even moral obligation to
keep up to a verbal commitment. So you're framing it as which
I really appreciate in terms of a legal technicality legally binding as
opposed to a moral imperative. Right. It might also be that the
nature of the assumptions that you can rely on are totally situated
in a given context in a given industry right? No like
totally like the labor law issues here are this is how we
do it here in this town everyone knows. Correct. Correct. So that
is what the Gemara has now limited it to say the debate
is about situations where the other side is relying on it. Okay
so that's going to but that means that Rabbi Yochanan a it
means that even Rabbi Yochanan understands there's sometimes it's okay to back
out but it what it means is that Rav who says it's
never a problem is even in the cases where you really would
want it to be a problem. So let's keep on reading. So
the Gemara says like this ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי u'mi amar
Rabbi Yochanan hachi did Rabbi Yochanan really say this? That if the
other side is not that דברים יש בהם משום מחוסרי אמנה? devarim
yesh bahem mishum mechusrei amana? I
forgot whether this is the limit of it. Okay
and let's take a look. Did Rabbi Yochanan really say this? דאמר
רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן האומר לחברו מתנה אני נותן
לך d'amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan ha'omer l'chavero matanah
ani noten lach right?
If you say to your friend I'm going to give you a
gift so יכול לחזור בו yachol lachzor bo you're able to retract
the agreement. יכול פשיטא yachol peshita of course you're able to you're
able to do a lot of things. Okay
when my wife edits my writing she always changes every time I
say can to may you know you can do this you actually
can do whatever you want but of course it's whether you may.
Anyway okay so יכול yachol of course you can do it אלא
מותר לחזור בו ela mutar lachzor bo rather you're allowed to. So
here Rabbi Yochanan says you're allowed to back out of an agreement.
So didn't Rabbi Yochanan say that you're not allowed to back out
of an agreement? So this is pushing us to the same type
of distinction that Rabbi Yochanan was only talking about certain types of
cases where the other side is relying on it. So let's take
a look. So the Gemara says so אמר רב פפא amar Rav
Papa ומודה רבי יוחנן במתנה מועטת דסמכא דעתייהו u'modeh Rabbi Yochanan be'matanah
mu'etet d'samcha da'atayu אלא מותר לחזור בו ela mutar lachzor bo right?
So it means that he's saying that it's permissible. So if it's
permissible how does how does that fit with what we are saying
before? So אמר רב פפא amar Rav Papa ומודה umodeh now let's
take out the vav מודה רבי יוחנן במתנה מועטת דסמכא דעתייהו modeh
Rabbi Yochanan be'matanah mu'etet d'samcha da'atayu no no no. The difference is
if I say I'm going to give you you know when I
die I'm going to give you all my estate like okay whatever.
But if I say you know I love you so much I'm
going to go ahead and buy you a car fine. But if
I actually say I'm going to give you a small gift that
you really do believe that it's going to happen and you're trusting
me right? Then that is מחוסרי אמנה. So מחוסרי אמנה is when
the other side the case here is דסמכא דעתייהו d'samcha da'atayu
they really rely on you. Now the interesting thing is presumably it's
opposed to when I say I'm going to buy the rest of
the flax you're presumably not looking around for other sellers for other
buyers I'm not looking around for other sellers like I'm giving up
opportunities. When I say I'm going to take the job and you're
going to say you're going to hire me I'm not you know
there's real opportunity loss. That's one degree of סמכא דעתייהו. samcha da'atayu.
I mean there you really want Rav to say at least that
it's morally wrong to back out. You know the case of מתנה
matanah is an interesting like middle case. Like you might be really
trusting me it's not like I discount it I really trust you
I'm really hoping for it but it doesn't mean that I've lost
anything you know I've given up any opportunity by believing that you
were going to give me the gift. Okay but nevertheless the fact
that I put my trust in you and I really believed in
and relied on it Rabbi Yochanan is saying it would be a
violation of that trust. to break, to back out, even if the
other side isn't losing anything. Okay, so רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan says
it's a problem when the other side relies on it and trusts
in you, even without any opportunity loss. רב seems to say even
with opportunity loss, there is not a problem of violation of trust.
Let's just look, read a little bit more. Okay, הכי נמי מסתברא,
hachi nami mistavra, that makes sense. דאמר רב אבין אמר רב יוחנן,
d'amar Rav Avin amar Rav Yochanan, ישראל שמה לבין לוי, Yisroel shama
l'ven Levi, כור מעשר יש לך בידי. kor maaser yesh lacha b'yadi.
ישראל Yisroel says to a לוי, Levi, you know, I've got a
measure of מעשר maaser in my granary, in my whatever, threshing floor,
that I'm going to give you. You're going to be the לוי
Levi I'm going to give the מעשר maaser to.
So בן לוי רשאי לעשותו תרומת מעשר במקום אחר. Ben Levi rashai
laasoto trumat maaser b'makom acher. So now this בן לוי Ben Levi
can go and he takes his other מעשר maaser that he has
in possession and say, that amount of מעשר maaser that that ישראל
Yisroel has in his threshing floor that he promised to give me,
that's going to be תרומת מעשר trumat maaser on this that I
have. Now that's pretty amazing because he doesn't yet own it, right?
So the ראשונים Rishonim don't even discuss that problem. I found an
אחרון Achronim that discusses it and he basically says since I promised
to give it to you and we're going to assume that like
רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan I'm going to keep my promise and whatever,
so you can be confident that you're going to get it. So
it's also sort of understood that therefore you, even though now it's
still technically mine, that you have, you have the right to, to
separate your מעשר maaser on, on the stuff that I, that I
own. Well, and the לוי Levi can now eat everything that he's
actually got in his house. Yeah, yeah, but if I said that
explicitly to you, I said to you, I'm going to let you,
I know you don't have a lot of money, whatever, you you
know, it's always taxes that kill you, you know, so you've got
this fruit but now you're really worried about having to separate מעשר,
maaser, I'll do you a favor. Okay, I'm wealthy, whatever, you can
just use my fruit for your, to separate your מעשר, maaser, and
I'm giving you the right to designate my fruit as מעשר maaser
on your fruit. That would work. Okay, you don't have to own
it. You have the right to use my fruit as מעשר maaser
on your fruit. So that's what's understood is sort of happening here.
Okay, even before the לוי Levi owns it. But it only works
because the לוי Levi can be confident he's going to get it
in the end. Because what would happen if he couldn't be confident
he's going to get it in the end? Even if I gave
him the right to do it, I might go ahead and give
it to someone else. I might have already given it to someone
else when he's off in his house thinking I'm still in my
house and being מפריש. mafrish. So the only thing that allows him
to be מפריש mafrish is his ability to be confident that he's
going to get it in the end. And that means he gets
it and gives it to a כהן, Kohen, in other words? What?
What does it mean get it in the end? I have to
give it to him and then he'll give it to a כהן,
Kohen, right? Yeah, yeah. Okay, but that's only because he can only
be מפריש mafrish if he can be confident that he's going to
get it in the end and that I haven't given it and
I won't give it to someone else. So let's take a look.
Okay. רשאי
לעשותו תרומת מעשר במקום אחר. rashai laasoto trumat maaser b'makom acher. אי
אמרת בשלמא לא מצו מהדר ביה, ei amrat bishlama lo matzu mehadar
bei, if I'm not allowed to go back, משום הכי רשאי, mishum
hachi rashai, that's why he's allowed to assume I'll still be holding
on to it and he can use it to be מפריש תרומות
ומעשרות, mafrish trumot u'maasrot, to be מפריש תרומת מעשר. mafrish trumat maaser.
אלא אי אמרת מצו מהדר ביה, ela ei amrat matzu mehadar bei,
but if I have a right to, to go back, אמאי רשאי,
amai rashai, why is he allowed to be מפריש? mafrish? אשתכח דקאכיל
טבלים, ishtakach d'kachil tavlim, it'll be,
it'll turn out that I gave it to somebody else and he's
eating טבל. tevel. So you see here this supports the idea of
רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan against רב that you make a verbal commitment
and the other side is relying on it and you know is
trusting you, therefore it is, you're not allowed to back out. And
otherwise there would be a fire in the end? Well okay that's,
that's unlikely. אלא אי אמרת, ela ei amrat, okay so now how
does this work according to רב? So the גמרא Gemara says הכא
במאי עסקינן כגון שנטלו הימנו וחזר והפקידו אצלו. hacha b'mai askinan k'gon
she'natlo heimenu v'chazar v'hipkido etzlo. All right, according to רב, we'll have
to say the case is I already gave the מעשר maaser to
the לוי Levi and he gave it back to me. Of course
then like what's the חידוש? chiddush? Then I'm just being שומר shomer
for him. אי הכי אימא סיפה, i hachi eima seifa, one minute,
if that's true, look at the last, second case of here. נתנו
לבן לוי אחר, natno l'ben levi acher, let's say I did back
out. I wasn't supposed to back out, but I did change my
mind and I did give it to a different לוי. Levi. אין
לו עליו אלא תרעומת. ein lo alav ela taromet. Then the first
guy he doesn't have any legal claim against me. He can make
a complaint. He can say you beepity beep you backed out on
your arrangement and I made all these assumptions. And he has, that's
a legitimate complaint, but he doesn't have any legal claim against me.
Okay what's the point of תרעומת taromet then if it doesn't have
any implications? I don't know, it means that we as a society
recognize that I did a wrong thing and that he has a
right to be offended and he has a right to object, but
nevertheless it doesn't have a legal claim. Okay anyway, ואי סלקא דעתך,
v'ei salka daatach, now first of all the point is, so this
is beautiful according to רב יוחנן, Rav Yochanan, right? I have a
moral commitment to see it through. He can rely on that moral
commitment, but because it's a moral commitment, if I violate it and
I do something else, what I did was legally binding when I
gave it to the person and there's no remaining legal claim. But
he was, but at least לכתחילה lechatchila he was able to rely
that I would live up to that moral commitment. But according to
רב that we're dealing that he took it and he gave it
back, so then why could I go ahead and give it to
somebody else? So ואי סלקא דעתך כגון שנטלו הימנו וחזר והפקידו אצלו,
v'ei salka daatach k'gon she'natlo heimenu v'chazar v'hipkido etzlo, that he took
it and then gave it back, that it really belonged to the
לוי, Levi, אמאי אין לו עליו אלא תרעומת, amai ein lo alav
ela taromet, why does he only have a complaint? כיון דמשכה ממוניה
גביה, keivan d'mashcha mamoneia gabeih,
since the לוי Levi took it and then he gave it back
to me, it's the first לוי's Levi money and I stole from
him when I gave it to somebody else.
You see that it's when he didn't take it. שמע מינה, shema
mina, that's a good point, which basically means that according to this
whole teaching, now this whole teaching is a teaching in the name
of Rabbi Yochanan. It's not a challenge to Rav, okay, this is
a Rabbi Yochanan teaching. So you see though that this is again,
so I don't know why the Gemara sort of said, I mean
it's just Rabbi Yochanan saying the same thing. We want to do
מצאנו מועד matzanu moed which we'll talk about. No, but you can't,
so it's just the same thing, it's just an illustration of the
position of Rabbi Yochanan we saw earlier. So you see there according
to Rabbi Yochanan, you are when the other side relies on it,
you are morally bound by it. The other side is really relying
on it because he's being מפריש תרומות ומעשרות. mafrish terumot u-ma'asrot. But
that's not legally binding, and you can go ahead and violate, you
can, you're not allowed to, but you can violate that, and then
the other side does not have a legal claim at all, only
has a moral claim against you. So that's Rabbi Yochanan which I
think makes a lot of sense to all of us. Rav's idea
that there's not even any moral obligation is pretty hard to understand.
Yeah, and in מצאנו מועד matzanu moed I had two questions on
that, you know, is that at all relative to your contextual... Yeah,
whatever, seems like it's very contextual. And the other thing is that,
you know, does that also depend on the closeness of the relationship?
Let's say, you know, it's a father and a son. The father
says, you know what, I know you're gonna inherit me all anyway,
I'm gonna give a hundred thousand dollars now, give back up. Yeah,
it sounds like it's all contextual. Okay, let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara Okay, תא שמע... ta shema... okay, שמע מינה. shema
mina.
ההוא גברא, hahu gavra, now a story, a certain man. יהב זוזי
אשומשמי, yehav zuzei a-shumshami,
that he gave money for sesame seeds. לסוף אייקר שומשמי, le-sof aykar
shumshami, in the end the value went up. So he, the other
side, would want to back out. הדרו בהו, hadru behu, they backed
out. ואמרו לית לן שומשמי, ve-amru leit lan shumshami,
we don't have any sesame seeds to give you, okay? שקול זוזך,
shkol zuzakh, take your money back. Now this, they would get a
מי שפרע, mi she-para. okay, because they actually... it was paid for.
So they're gonna get a מי שפרע. mi she-para. But we're moving
on now to a different question of what... we'll see. לסוף לא
שקל
זוזי, le-sof lo shakal zuzei, he didn't... he says, no, I'm not
taking my money back, you give me the sesame seeds. And he
refused to take his money back.
Okay, לא שקל
זוזי. lo shakal zuzei. איגנוב, ignov, then the money was stolen from
the people from the sellers of the sesame seeds. Okay, so the
question is, what is their relationship to that money? They retracted the
sale, they wanted to give him the money back, he refused to
take it. Is that money now, are they a שומר shomer on
that money? Are they liable for loss of that money? Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. אתו לקמיה דרבא, atu le-kamei de-Rava,
came to Rava. אמר ליה כיון דאמרי לך לך שקול זוזך, amar
lei keivan de-amri lakh lekh shkol zuzakh,
since they said here's your money, take it, ולא שקלת, ve-lo shaklat,
and you refused to take it, so לא מיבעיא שומר שכר דלא
הוי ליה, lo mibaya shomer sakhar delo havei lei,
it goes without saying that they're not a שומר שכר shomer sakhar
on it, they're not paid people, you're not paying them to watch
it, right? אלא אפילו שומר חנם נמי לא הוי, ela afilu shomer
hinam nami lo havei,
they're not even a שומר חנם. shomer hinam. You know, just cause
you refused to take your money from their house, like you know,
if I go ahead and I'm your guest for dinner and I,
well maybe that's a little different because then at least temporarily you're
watching my money back, but anyway. And I leave my coat in
your... and I'm walking out, you say, wait wait wait, you're forgetting
your coat! And you say no, I refuse to take my coat,
you keep it, I don't want it, take your coat, and just
walk out. Am I a שומר shomer because you left your coat
by me? Okay, so you refused to take the money, I didn't
want your money. So they're saying you're not even a שומר shomer
on it, okay? So he can't use that coat though, can he?
Right, so they can't use the money. Okay, I'm going to talk
a little bit about that later. But they have that money and
they don't want it anymore. So the
גמרא Gemara. says, okay, the market changed. Right, the market changed. He's
trying to make money back after by saying I don't want to
take... No, he's saying I still... you still give me back my
sesame seeds. You give me the sesame seeds we agreed
on. I don't want to reverse this sale. I don't accept that
you want to reverse this sale. I want my sesame seeds. But
the point is they're entitled to reverse it. It's not like he's
giving away his money. He wants them to keep the money so
he can get his sesame seeds. But they're saying we're refusing to
do that. And then he's gonna lose money... and he just walked
out. So that's what we have to figure... so what's now, where...
what are we left with? His money by them that they didn't
want to be a שומר shomer on, okay? So the גמרא Gemara
says, okay, so לא הוי. lo havei. You're not liable. אמרו ליה
רבנן לרבא, amru lei rabanan le-Rava, now the Rabbis said to Rava,
הא בעי לקבולי עליה מי שפרע. ha bei lekabulei alei mi she-para.
Ah, you see, I'm sorry, when I gave my overview it was
really a preview. I was looking for the גמרא. Gemara So he
says, one minute, he has to accept... they have to accept a
מי שפרע. Mi She-Para. Now this is a new concept. I have
accepted the money, I have a right to reverse the sale, but
I get a מי שפרע. Mi She-Para So apparently the question is,
at what stage is the sale reversed, okay? So when I say
I'm reversing it? It sounds like here, since the consequence of reversing
is getting a מי שפרע, Mi She-Para? I have to accept the
מי שפרע. Mi She-Para And that therefore reverses the sale. So what
does that mean? So that means the other side says, well if
you're going to back out then you're going to get a מי
שפרע. Mi She-Para? So fine, I accept the... like what's the... what's
the process there? It's parallel to a שבועה, shavuah, like if you're
really willing to be in
this position, take the שבועה. shavuah. I understand, alright, I understand. I'm
just saying like... Like let's say the other side doesn't know this
law of מי שפרע. Mi She-Para I mean, I guess probably everybody
must know this law of מי שפרע Mi She-Para, because it probably
is a regular thing about backing out. But the question is like
let's say do you have to demand that I make a מי
שפרע? Mi She-Para Do I have to get up and say, let's
say I want to back out and you don't want me to
back out? So if you don't want me to back out, you're
not going to demand the מי שפרע Mi She-Para. from me. So
then I mean I just don't get exactly what's the... do I
have to get up and say I am backing out and accept
the מי שפרע? Mi She-Para, Like what's the act that's done to
be the קבלת מי שפרע? kabbalat Mi She-Para? But anyway, one way
or another the גמרא Gemara is saying that until the side accepts
the מי שפרע Mi She-Para the sale is not yet reversed. Okay,
and therefore if the sale isn't reversed, if you gave me money
for the sale and I have not reversed it yet and I
lost your money, I don't say well like I'm not liable for
it. I took that money and I either have to give it
back to you or give you what we agreed upon. So until
the sale is reversed, I'm fully liable for that money. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says it's all very nice if they accepted the
מי שפרע, Mi She-Para then they've reversed the sale and the money
is the other side's then he doesn't want to take it back,
that's his problem. Okay, but if they haven't accepted the מי שפרע
Mi She-Para the sale is still valid and then you have to
give either the money or the sesame seeds. Okay, so the גמרא
says אביי לקבולי עליה מי שפרע, Abaye le-kabulei alei Mi She-Para, אמר
ליה הכי נמי. amar leh hachi nami. So he said to them
okay, הכי נמי, hachi nami, so meaning okay, he has to accept
the מי שפרע. Mi She-Para? Now what does that mean? Does it
mean that he already accepted it when this happened or does it
mean he can accept it now and now that he agrees to
it then retroactively it means that the sale was
reversed, right? I understand, but when רבא Rava is saying you're right,
he has to accept the מי שפרע, Mi She-Para, does it mean
you're right and he did accept the מי שפרע Mi She-Para before
the money got lost or whatever? Or does it mean that as
long as they accept the מי שפרע Mi She-Para. now in court,
retroactively the sale was reversed and so on? So that's there's a
new idea here, that there needs to be a formal acceptance of
a מי שפרע Mi She-Para. to reverse the sale. And the question
is does it have to... is it only after it's accepted that
the sale is considered reversed or once it's accepted then retroactively? You
know, so like it's not
clear. Not clear, I have no idea. Maybe, maybe, I don't know.
How could he have gotten back in that order and say well
where would the מי שפרע? mi shepara. Because you want to back
out and then I say you're not allowed to back out, you're
going to get a מי שפרע, mi shepara you're going to be
cursed. And you say
well let God curse you. I think it probably worked more by
saying you'll get a מי שפרע mi shepara. and you'll say fine,
I'll get a מי שפרע. mi shepara. Okay, so anyway, okay. אמר
רב פפא, amar Rav Papa,
אמר לי רבינא. amar li Ravina. So now that's one version of
the story, which is very interesting about you know this new idea
of accepting a מי שפרע. mi shepara. Now רבא Rava said, רבינא
Ravina said to me, לדידי אמר לי ההוא מרבנן, li didi amar
li hahu me-rabbanan, I personally was told by a certain rabbi, רב
טוביומי שמיה, Rav Tuvyumi shemeih, his name was רב טוביומי, Rav Tuvyumi,
ואמרי לה רב שמואל בר זוטרא שמיה ve-amri lah Rav Shmuel bar
Zutra shemeih or something, it was a different
rabbi. דההוא יהבי ליה כל חללא
דעלמא לא הוי כמשני בדיבוריה, de-hahu yahvi leh kal halala de-alma lo
hava kemishani be-diburei, that
this rabbi said to me, look, a rabbi came to me and
he said I was the person in this event. I was the
person who was the seller of the sesame seeds and the money
and the whole thing. And I want to tell you first of
all that if somebody would have given me all of the wealth
in the world, I would never go back on a promise and
a commitment that I had made. Okay, so that's getting back to
the דבר היפה משום נכסי אמנה. Davar Ha-Yafe Mi-shum Nikhsei Amanah. You
got the story wrong. I'm going to tell you what the story
was, but if if but I was the principal of that story
of the guy who was like not giving back you know you
know sort of the the question about the other guy's money, and
I want to tell you that if he had actually... that I
would never have backed out on a deal. כל חללא, kal halala,
all the everything in the world, everything in the cavity of the
world. No, no, no, whatever, I don't... anyway, okay, so so he
basically says the story here started that the sellers of the sesame
seeds wanted to back out, right? And he says no, no, no,
I was that principal and it was not backing out. I would
never back out on anything and any commitment that I had made.
לא הוי משני בדיבוריה. lo hava meshani be-diburei. Okay, לדידי הוי עובדא,
li didi hava uvda, this happened to me, I was the principal
of this story. ההוא יומא אפניא דמעלי שבתא הוה, hahu yoma apanya
di-ma'ali shabta hava, that day,
it was right before it was Friday late Friday afternoon, right before
שבת. Shabbat. הוה יתיבנא ואתא ההוא גברא וקאי אבבא, hava yativna ve-ata
hahu gavra ve-ka'i a-baba,
somebody came and knocked on the door. אמר לי, amar li, he
said to me, אית לך שומשמי לזבוני? it lach shumshami le-zabuni?
Hey, do you have some sesame seeds to sell? There it was,
ten minutes before שקיעה, shkiya, candle lighting. אמינא ליה, amina leh, I
said to him, לא! lo! No! So somehow this story got perverted
that I sold some sesame seeds and promised and retract. That's not
what happened. He asked me for sesame seeds, I said no. אמר
לי, amar li, להוו הנך זוזי בפיקדון גבך, le-havu hanach zuzei be-pikadon
gabach,
okay look, but I got to go home, I got this ten
thousand dollars, I was looking in the market... marketplace to buy sesame
seeds, it's about to be שבת *Shabbos*. Can I just leave the
money by you? It's going to be שבת *Shabbos*. דחשלי *De-chasheli*, it's
getting dark. אמרי ליה *Amrei lei*, I said to him, הא ביתא
קמך *Ha beisa kamach*, look, here's my house. אותבינהו בביתא *Osvinu be-beisa*,
if you... so I guess my house is here. Okay? I did
not agree to be a שומר *shomer*. I said my house is
here. He put it in the house. ואיגנוב *Ve-ignov*, and then it
was stolen. אתא לקמיה דרבא *Osa le-kamei de-Rava*, came to רבא *Rava*.
אמרי ליה *Amrei lei*, רבא *Rava* said, כל הא ביתא קמך *kol
hai beisa kamach*, look, if you say to a person, somebody says
let me... can you be a שומר *shomer* and you say, look,
you know, my house is here, that's all you say. Okay? So
I'm not going to prevent you from leaving it in my house.
That's essentially what you're saying. So if you say that, I'm not
going to stop you, it's ערב שבת *Erev Shabbos*, I'm not going
to stop you from leaving it in my house. So לא מיבעיא
שומר שכר דלא הוי *lo mi-ba'ei shomer sachar de-lo havei*, it goes
without saying that you're not a שומר שכר *shomer sachar*, אלא אפילו
שומר חינם נמי לא הוי *ela afilu shomer chinam nami lo havei*,
you're not even a שומר חינם *shomer chinam*. Okay? אמרי ליה *Amrei
lei*, והא אמרי ליה רבנן לרבא *ve-ha amrei lei rabbanan le-Rava*, איבעי
ליה לקבולי עליה מי שפרע mi shepara *iba'ei lei lekabulei alei mi-she-para*.
One minute, but the version of the story that we have is
that then the Rabbis pushed back on רבא *Rava* when he said
that you're not a שומר *shomer*, what about the
מי שפרע mi shepara *mi-she-para*? So אמר לא היו דברים מעולם *Amar
lo haya devarim me-olam*. Yeah, that wasn't true. That wasn't part of
the... that's not a true part of the story either. You guys
got the whole story wrong, okay? I don't know, maybe there were
two stories that were very similar. Anyway, what's really fascinating besides this
issue of when are you a שומר *shomer*, is this idea that
A, you have to accept a מי שפרע mi shepara, *mi-she-para*, and
B, right, this question about... and I just want to say a
second about this because it's a big debate in the רי"ף *Rif*,
the רא"ש *Rosh*, and the גאונים *Gaonim*. When I give you money
for a sale, this gets back to the question of how do
you review
it at this stage? I've given you money, forget before I... I
give you money and the money gets stolen. Okay? It's not that
you've retracted yet. Are you a שומר שכר *shomer sachar* or שומר
חינם *shomer chinam* on my money? Or do we say no, actually,
since I'm giving you money there's an assumption we're going to go
through with the sale, according to some understandings the sale's already binding,
it could just be reversed, so you actually now own the money
and have rights to use it, and now it's like a הלוואה
*halva'ah*, it's like a loan, and therefore if something happens, even an
אונס ones *oness* happens, this is what we would hope would happen.
I paid you the thousand dollars, you haven't given me the thing
yet. Even if an אונס *oness* happens, you're either going to give
me the property that you promised or you're going to give me
my thousand dollars back, right? So that's what we would tend to
assume, and that's basically how the ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim* פסקן pasken *pasken*.
That once I give you the money you're basically
a בעל *ba'al*... into the down payment... not a down payment, but
it's the money as opposed to the משיכה *meshikhah*, so even though
the sale is not final final, you're considered to own the money
and now you either owe me the money back or you owe
me the object. Okay? But in this case, right, the money had
not yet been spent. The original money was still there and the
side had reversed it. So in the combination of those two, the
money hadn't been spent, the original money was there, and the side
had reversed it, then they said now that we're reversing it, if
we're reversing it and we spent the money then we just owe
you the money. But if we're reversing it and it's the original
money, then that money now is fully yours and you don't want
to take it and we don't want to take it, we're not
a שומר *shomer* on it, and that was sort of that version
of that case. Okay? But the bigger question was דברים משום מחוסרי
אמנה *devarim mishum mechusrei amanah*, where again basically the ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim*
agree דברים יש בהם משום מחוסרי אמנה *devarim yesh bahem mishum mechusrei
amanah* when the other side relies on it or trusts in you
and the question is what are the circumstances. So let's very quickly
read to the משנה *Mishnah*, okay? רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, I'm just
going to read to the משנה *Mishnah*. רבי שמעון אומר כל שהכסף
בידו ידו על העליונה *Rabbi Shimon omer kol she-hakessef be-yado yado al
ha-elyona*. רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says the guy who received the money,
he has the right to retract, the seller has the right to
retract, not the buyer. So the גמרא *Gemara* says תנא אמר רבי
שמעון אימתי בזמן שהכסף והפירות ביד מוכר *Tana, amar Rabbi Shimon: eimatai?
Bizman she-hakessef ve-hapeirot be-yad mokher*. When is it that they can retract?
If the seller has the money and the fruit. אבל כסף ביד
מוכר
פירות ביד לוקח אינו יכול לחזור בו *Aval kessef be-yad mokher, peirot
be-yad lokei'ach, eino yakhol lachzor
bo*, because the money's in his hands. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
בידו *be-yado*, what do you mean in his hands? Sounds like the
money's in the hands of the buyer, because רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*
says the guy who has the money can retract, according to here
the whole exchange has already happened. ביד מוכר הוא *Be-yad mokher hu*,
the money's in the hands of the seller. No, אלא מפני שדמי
כספו בידו *ela mi-pnei she-dmei kaspo be-yado*. No, no, it means that
here the sale cannot be reversed because the buyer got the value
for his money, he got the object. So this is almost like
an obvious statement, it says when the whole sale has gone through,
you paid the money and you got the object, now you can't
retract. פשיטא *Peshita*, obviously. אמר רבא הכא hacha, במאי עסקינן *Amar Rava:
hakha be-mai askinan*, what are we talking about? דהוות עלייה של לוקח
מושכרת ביד מוכר *De-havsa aliyah shel lokei'ach muskeres be-yad mokher*. No, no,
what we mean that the object is in the possession of the
buyer, it doesn't mean it's literally in the possession. It's on the
property of the buyer but he hasn't taken possession of it yet.
How could that be? Because the seller is renting a house from
the buyer. Okay? So the seller has his fruit in the buyer's
house, but the buyer doesn't have possession of it. Because since the
seller is renting it, it's considered in the seller's for this time
period in the seller's... possession. Okay, כגון שהיתה עלייה של לוקח מושכרת
ביד מוכר. So now, if that's true, if it's in the buyer's
house but the buyer doesn't have possession, why can why can he
not reverse it? The sale shouldn't be final, he didn't take possession
yet. Because טעמא מאי תקינו רבנן משיכה, taama mai takinu rabanan meshicha,
why did the rabbis say that you have to take possession before
you and until you take possession it can be reversed? גזירה שמא
יאמרו נשרפו חטיך בעלייה gezeira shema yomru nisrefu chitecha bealiyah because we're
afraid if you don't take possession the seller will say, "Hey, your
stuff burned and it was an אונס and I'm sorry, you're out
your object." Okay, so the גמרא says הכא, here, that it's in
the buyer's house even if technically it's rented to the seller, but
ברשותא דלוקח נינהו bershuta delokeach ninhu it's in the buyer's house, so
the buyer can do what's necessary to protect the object. Okay, even
though the seller is renting the house. איניש בדליכא באונס, Inish bedleika
beones, even if a fire breaks out by some, you know, accident
and not controllable, איהו טרח ומציל ihu tarach umatzil he'll protect it.
Okay. One last story. ההוא גברא דיהב זוזי אחמרא, Hahu gavra deyahav
zuzei achamra, a certain person gave money. Now I gotta tell you,
whenever I see buying אחמרא achamra I always assume it means wine,
but here the ראשונים Rishonim say חמור. chamor. I don't know how
they know whether it's talking about wine or a donkey, what does
your English translation have? Wine? Wine. So some ראשונים say, I mean
normally it's always a wine in this context, a number of ראשונים
say חמור. chamor. Anyway, but I'm going to read it wine. Okay,
a certain person gave money for wine, ולסוף שמע דקא בעו למנסביה
ulesof shama deka ba'u limnesavei דבי פרזיק רופילא. debei parzik rufila. So
and then he heard that they wanted to, how do they translate
that, to get married to or to take it, what do they
say?
Requisition. It's a requisition it, appropriate it, fine. Okay, anyway, so the
house of פרזיק Parzik was the name of somebody's name, and רופילא
rufila is a like a government officer or general or whatever. Anyway,
he heard that the government wanted to, was going to seize the
wine. And they didn't care whose possession it was in. So he
paid for the wine, he did not want to take possession, he
wanted to retract because the wine was about to be seized. Okay,
so אמרי ליה הבו לי זוזי לא בעינא חמרא, Amri lei havu
li zuzei lo beina chamra, "Give me back my money, I don't
want the wine." כי אתא לקמיה דרב חסדא, Ki ata likamei deRav
Chisda, he came to Rav Chisda, אמר ליה amar lei he said
to him, כדרך שתקנו משיכה במוכרין כך תקנו משיכה בלקוחות. Kederech shetiknu
meshicha bemochrin kach tiknu meshicha belokachot. Yeah, we don't פסקן like רב
שמעון, Rav Shimon, not only can the seller back out, the buyer
can also back out as long as the, you know, even after
the money changed hands, as long as he has not taken possession.
Now, what should you say though he should get? He should get
a מי שפרע. mi shepara So here a number of ראשונים say
no, you don't get a מי שפרע mi shepara, in these cases.
In these cases where there is like a serious loss and you're
really just protecting yourself against, it's not just you're changing a deal
in the normal fluctuations of the market, this type of a case
you don't even get a מי שפרע. So it's a really interesting
continuum, right? When you just arbitrarily back out you get a מי
שפרע. When there's like a good reason to back out you don't
even get a מי שפרע. What about if it's normal type of
price fluctuation? Is that a good reason, not a good reason? Do
you get a מי שפרע or not? There's some debate about that.
Okay, let's say though you didn't even give money. Is it considered
a violation of trust to back out? Right, so there's questions about
how much does the other side rely on you, but there's also
questions about how much do you stand to lose? Are you just
arbitrarily changing your mind, right, or are you, you know, or are
you doing it because you're going to suffer a serious loss? So
the question about when exactly you get a מי שפרע and when
exact, like how much are you allowed to protect your own interest
and not get a מי שפרע, when exactly even according to רב
יוחנן Rav Yochanan it's considered a violation of trust without a מי
שפרע in terms of how much does that side rely on you
and trust in you and how much are you protecting your own
interest, right? There's a whole range of different factors in terms of
that. Okay, but it is interesting that again, on the one hand
רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan says that there's definitely cases where there's no
מי שפרע, the cases where there's not, no violation of trust and
the side didn't really rely on you, and then there are cases
where those things do come into factor. Yeah. Last case.